Finding Aid for Albert A. Applegate papers 1963-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert A. Applegate papers 1963-1973
Applegate, Albert A.
Administrative assistant to George Romney, governor of Michigan and U. S. Secretary of Housing and Urban Development. papers include correspondence, personnel reports, memoranda, and background files concerning Applegate's work as Romney's aide and speech writer.
85656 Aa 2
17 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Applegate papers (Donor no. 4703 ) came to the library as part of the various George Romney accessions.
The collection is open for research.
Albert A. Applegate was born December 3, 1928. A graduate of Princeton University's Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs, Applegate received a master's degree in political science from the University of Michigan, where he held a Ford Foundation fellowship in political behavior research. After receiving his degree, Applegate joined the faculty of Eastern Michigan University as an assistant professor of political science.
In 1963, he joined the staff of newly elected Michigan governor George Romney as administrative assistant to the governor for program development. In 1965, Applegate was named administrative assistant for communications-research. In this capacity, Applegate was Romney's principal speech-writer, responsible for most of the governor's major gubernatorial addresses as well as for those campaign speeches made by Romney in his quest for the Republican nomination for the presidency. He served in this capacity until his resignation on January 21, 1969.
When Romney joined the Nixon administration as secretary of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, Applegate followed him, serving as his executive assistant and speech-writer. Applegate also served with Romney in his work with the National Center for Voluntary Action and the Concerned Citizens Movement.
The papers document Applegate's close working relationship with George Romney in his campaign for the presidency, as staff member in the Department of Housing and Urban Development, and as one of his staff at the National Center for Voluntary Action.
The collection has been divided into six series: Chronological, 1963-1972; Background Files, 1963-1973; U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Affairs, 1969-1972; National Center for Voluntary Action, 1969-1973; Voluntary Action Background Files, 1969-1973; and European Trip, 1970. The researcher should note that the great value of the Applegate papers is as a supplement to the various series in the George Romney collection. The researcher is urged to begin with the inventories to the Romney papers before turning to the Applegate papers.
Subjects:
Applegate, Albert A.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.; Voluntarism.; Governors--Michigan.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.
- Chronological Files
  The Chronological series (2 linear feet; 1963-1972) consists of copies of memoranda sent to Romney (first as governor, then as cabinet secretary) and letters received and responses sent. This latter type of document includes those letters that Applegate wrote but that went out under Romney's name and copies of letters that Applegate received for his information.
  - Memoranda
    - 1963-1966, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1967-1968, 1 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - 1969-1972, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1971, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Background Files 1963-1973, 1969-1973, 10 linear feet
  Background Files (10 linear feet; 1963-1973) includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, press releases and clippings, and other collected materials that Applegate accumulated in his position as administrative assistant to Governor (later Secretary) Romney. The files, although largely relating to Applegate's (and Romney's) work at HUD, also concern the governor's unsuccessful bid for the Republican nomination for President in 1968. For this reason, the researcher interested in 1960s politics should consult both this series as well as the Romney Associates series of the George Romney collection.
  - ABM (Box 2)
  - ACTION (Box 2)
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (Box 2)
  - Airlie House--HUD Summer Seminar August 6-7, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Alinsky, Saul (Box 2)
  - Amendatory Policy (Urban renewal) (Box 2)
  - American Revolution Bicentennial (Box 2)
  - Audit reports (Sections 235-236) January-February 1972 (Box 2)
  - Aumente, Jerome (Box 2)
  - Beecher School District, Flint, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Black Caucus Response May 1971 (Box 2)
  - Boyer, Gay (Box 2)
  - Breakthrough (Operation Breakthrough)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Cabinet Committee on Construction (Box 3)
  - Camp David--HUD meeting May 1969 (Box 3)
  - Camp David 1971 (Box 3)
  - Camp David--Regional administrators meeting April 1972 (Box 3)
  - Civil Rights (Box 3)
  - Community Self-Determination Act (Box 3)
  - Consumer protection (Box 3)
  - Counseling (235) Task Force (Box 3)
  - Current reading and review for GR 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - DeJonge, Herbert C (Box 3)
  - Departmental Communications Meetings with Assistant Secretaries (Box 3)
  - Detroit, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Domestic Council (Box 3)
  - Downs, Anthony (Box 3)
  - Duke, Dorothy S (Box 3)
  - Economists meeting 1967 (Box 3)
  - Education--Federal aid 1966 (Box 3)
  - Federal Housing Opportunity guidelines (Box 3)
  - Esch, Marvin (Box 3)
  - Fair housing
    - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 3)
  - Farmer, Gene (Life Magazine) 1967 (Box 3)
  - Federal-state relations
    - 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Spiro Agnew paper) (Box 3)
  - Financial staff and procedures (Box 3)
  - Fisher, Max M (Box 3)
  - Fitzwater, John (Box 3)
  - Foreign policy briefings 1967 (Box 3)
  - Forrester, Jay W (Box 4)
  - Freedom of Information (Box 4)
  - Friedman, Milton (Box 4)
  - "Future of the City" meeting September 1971 (Box 4)
  - Garrity, Margaret (Box 4)
  - Gottehrer, Dean (Box 4)
  - Government spending (Box 4)
  - Hanna, Willard (Box 4)
  - Harris, T. George (Look Magazine) (Box 4)
  - Hart, Philip A (Box 4)
  - Home Furnishings Council (Box 4)
  - Housing (Box 4)
  - Housing Allowance Review Group (Box 4)
  - Housing and Urban Development Act of 1969 (Box 4)
  - Housing and Urban Development Act of 1970 (Box 4)
  - Housing Finance (Box 4)
  - Housing Management (Box 4)
  - Housing Management (and training) Review Group (Box 4)
  - Housing Production (Box 4)
  - HUD Advisory Committee
    - Budget
      - 1970 (Box 4)
      - 1971 (Box 4)
      - 1972 (Box 4)
      - 1973 (Box 4)
      - 1974 (Box 4)
    - Central Office Organization Stage II (Box 5)
    - Departmental staff meetings (Box 5)
    - Departmental Voluntary Action Projects (Box 5)
    - Elderly programs (Box 5)
    - Employees Task Force Against Racism (Box 5)
    - Issue papers (Box 5)
    - Legislation 1971 (Box 5)
    - Mail procedures (Box 5)
    - Operating Committee working file and agendas 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Organization 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Posture papers 1970 (Box 6)
    - Procurement contracting study (Box 6)
    - Program management (Box 6)
    - Regional administrators meetings (Box 6)
    - Transition (Box 6)
    - Secretary's office organization (Box 6)
    - Summaries (Box 6)
  - Hudson Institute (Box 6)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. 1968 (Box 6)
    (re position on Vietnam)
  - Hunger 1965 (Box 6)
  - Indian affairs (Box 6)
  - Industrialized housing (Box 6)
  - Inflation (Box 6)
  - Interest rates (Box 6)
  - Interagency meetings 1972 (Box 6)
  - Intergovernmental Personnel Act (Box 6)
  - Kelly, John M (Box 6)
  - Kissinger, Henry 1967 (Box 6)
  - Land policy (Box 6)
  - Latin America (Box 6)
  - Leadership (Box 6)
  - Leadership Council for Metropolitan Open Communities (Box 6)
  - Lincoln Day--proposed inserts to speeches (Box 6)
  - Lodge, George C (Box 6)
  - McKinney, Harold (memoranda), 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Michigan City (Ind.)--All-American City Award 1966 (Box 7)
  - Minority enterprise (Box 7)
  - Model cities (Box 7)
  - Modernizing state government materials (Box 7)
  - Mould, Christopher M (Box 7)
  - Nader, Ralph (Box 7)
  - National Growth Policy (Box 7)
  - National Growth Policy presentation and memoranda November-December 1970 (Box 7)
  - National Growth Policy Report--Chapter VII--New Initiatives (Box 8)
  - National Growth Policy Report December 1970 (Box 8)
  - Negative Income Tax (Box 8)
  - Neighborhood Development Program (Box 8)
  - Nixon Administration program 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Nixon-Romney conference re self-help, private enterprise and voluntary urban programs 1968 (Box 8)
  - O'Brien, Thomas 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - Pianin, Eric (Box 8)
  - Press matters (Box 8)
  - Pruitt-Igoe, St. Louis, Missouri 1971 (Box 8)
  - Public housing (Box 8)
  - Public Housing Management Review Group (Box 8)
  - Public order (Box 8)
  - Reagan, Ronald: Letter and comments about campaign brochure 1968 (Box 8)
  - Rehabilitation (Box 8)
  - Republican Task Forces--Michigan 1968 (Box 8)
  - Research Project Review Groups (Box 9)
  - Right to work (Box 9)
  - Romney interviews (Box 9)
  - Romney presidential eligibility (Box 9)
  - Romney--possible senate candidacy 1969 (Box 9)
  - Romney, Lenore--campaign organization 1970 (Box 9)
  - Rubin, Marvin R (Box 9)
  - Rutledge, Aaron (Box 9)
  - Saginaw, Michigan, urban renewal (Box 9)
  - Self-help housing (Box 9)
  - Seneca, Martin (Box 9)
  - Senior citizens 1965 (Box 9)
  - Speech assignment schedules (Box 9)
  - Speech drafts (non-Applegate) (Box 9)
  - Speech notes and ideas (Box 9)
  - Speechwriter meetings (Box 9)
  - Staff notes (Michigan) (Box 9)
  - Staff reduction implementation (HUD) (Box 9)
  - State housing programs (Box 9)
  - Streit, Clarence K (Box 9)
  - Tenant selection and assignment policy 1970 (Box 9)
  - Thomas, Nicholas P (Box 9)
  - TOP (The Optional Process) meetings 1972 (Box 9)
  - Troilo, Arthur C (Box 9)
  - United Republicans of America (Box 9)
  - Urban crisis project inventory 1968 (Box 9)
  - Urban dynamics (Box 9)
  - Urban dynamics--Morgan Doughton (Box 9)
  - Urban dynamics--Chris Sower (Box 9)
  - Urban and racial material (Box 9)
  - Urban Grant University (Box 9)
  - Urban projects (Box 9)
  - Urban Tour 1967 (Box 10)
    (George Romney's tour of urban areas in the United States as part of his presidential campaign)
  - Urban University working file (Box 11)
  - Vietnam
    - 1965 (Box 11)
    - 1966 (Box 11)
    - Quakers (Box 11)
  - Volunteer planning (Box 11)
  - Walsh, E.F (Box 11)
  - Wilhoite, Ken (Box 11)
  - World concept 1966 (Box 11)
  - Yoh, Bernard (Box 11)
  - Youth lectures (Box 11)
  - Youth programs-Summer (Box 11)
- U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development 1969-1972, 0.5 linear feet
  - Subject files (unprocessed) (Box 12)
- National Center for Voluntary Action
  (and predecessor organizations)
  - 1969-1973 (Box 13)
- Voluntary Action Background Files 1969-1973, 1 linear feet
  - A-M (Box 14)
  - N-S (Box 15)
  - S-Y (Box 16)
  - [unprocessed] .5 linear ft (Box 16)
- European Trip 1970
  - Romney's inspection of European housing programs 1970 (Box 17)
Related Material
The George Romney Papers should be consulted before using the Applegate papers. Many speeches written by Applegate can be found in the Romney Papers under Governor's Papers/Governor's Office/Press Office.